Frances Carpenter Papers 1917-1972
Sophia Smith Collection
Frances Carpenter papers
1917-1972
Carpenter, Frances, 1890-1972
MS 81
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Children's author, Geographer, Author. The Carpenter Papers include correspondence; writings; original manuscripts of The Story of East Africa and South American Wonder Tales; radio talk transcripts on topics such as children's books and "women of the arts"; and five scrapbooks consisting of photographs, clippings, illustrations, bibliographies, reviews, and book jackets.
Frances Carpenter was born in Washington, D.C. on April 30, 1890 to Joanna Condict and Frank G. Carpenter. She graduated from Smith College in 1912. Her father was a foreign correspondent and travelled extensively. Frances accompanied him on many of his travels as secretary and photographer. They co-authored several books including The Foods We Eat (1925), The Clothes We Wear (1926), and The Houses We Live In (1926). She also wrote Ourselves and Our City (1928), The Ways We Travel (1929), Tales of a Basque Grandmother (1930) Our Little Friends of Eskimo Land (1931) Our Neighbors Near and Far, An Elementary Geography (1932), and other books. In 1960 she edited a book of articles her father had written in the 1880s about life in Washington, D.C. entitled Carp's Washington (1960). She married W. Chapin Huntington, commercial attaché at the American Embassy in Paris. She was Vice President of the International Society of Woman Geographers, a Fellow of the Royal Geography Society of London, and President of the Smith College Alumnae Association and on the Smith College Board of Trustees. She died November 2, 1972.
The Frances Carpenter Papers include correspondence (primarily with publishers); original manuscripts of The Story of East Africa and South American Wonder Tales; radio talk transcripts on topics such as children's books and "women of the arts"; and five scrapbooks consisting of photographs, clippings, illustrations, bibliographies, reviews, and book jackets.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Frances Carpenter Huntington donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from in 1965 and 1969.
Carpenter, Frances, 1890-1972; Carpenter, Frank G. (Frank George), 1855-1924; Children's literature--Authorship; Geographers--United States--Biography--Sources; Women geographers--United States--Biography--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources
Frank G. Carpenter Papers (father) in the SSC.
Many books on famous women in the SSC were donated by Frances Carpenter Huntington (some are now in Neilson Library).
The Frank and Frances Carpenter photograph collection at the Library of Congress.
The Frances Carpenter Collection of scrapbooks at the Library of Congress
Records of the Society of Woman Geographers are also at the Library of Congres.
- Correspondence
  - American Book Company 1950-55 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Doubleday & Co. 1935-68 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Follett Publishing Company 1968-69 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - McCormick-Mathers of American Book Company 1966-68 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Junior Literary Guild 1930-55 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Knopf, Washington D.C. 1957-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Red Cross 1934-59 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence about writings
    - "African Wonder Tales" 1962-63 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Arabian Desert" 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Basque Grandmother" 1928-42, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Chinese Grandmother" 1936-59 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "The Elephant's Bath Tub" 1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Horses and Heroes" 1950-66, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Korean Grandmother" 1946-65, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "The Mouse Palace" 1963-64, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Pocahontas and Her World" 1951-66 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Russian Grandmother" 1923-36, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Seas and Ships" (Doubleday) 1958-60, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "South American Wonder Tales" (includes transcript) 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "The Story of East Africa" (includes transcript), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "The Story of Korea" 1965-69 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Swiss Grandmother" 1939-41, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Wonder Tales of Dogs and Cats" 1953-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Radio and TV Talks: transcripts 1942-48, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Ladies of the Literary": transcript 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- People from the Sky
  - Snapshot and cover 1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Gallery proofs undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Illustrations by Betty Fraserundated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Oversize materials
  - Binder of children's book covers and illustrations, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1917-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 1928-40 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 1942-62 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1962-72 (Box 4, Folder 2)